lifelabs.com 2019-04-12

# Privacy Policy – LifeLabs

At LifeLabs, we are committed to maintaining the highest standards of privacy, confidentiality and data security including the personal health information of our patients. This is fundamental to achieving our goal in providing enhanced patient care. LifeLabs has robust privacy policies, procedures and training in place that are in compliance with applicable privacy laws.   
We will only collect, use and disclose your personal information lawfully and responsibly in order to provide our services to you. 

## Purpose of Collection, Use and Disclosure   
of Your Personal Information

LifeLabs policies are governed by the Personal Health Information Protection Act, 2004 (PHIPA) in the province of Ontario, the Personal Information Protection Act (PIPA) in the province of British Columbia and the Health Information Protection Act (HIPA) in Saskatchewan. 

## Why We Collect and Use

LifeLabs only collects and uses the personal health information we require to provide our services to you. We collect and use your personal health information: 

  * To verify your identity (e.g. when you visit one of our patient service centres, when you sign up for LifeLabs’ _my results_ TM Portal (Ontario) and/or _my eHealth_ TM (British Columbia)
  * To provide you quality laboratory services
  * To match your specimens with your test results
  * To manage your account and provide you support when you contact our customer service centre
  * To plan, evaluate and monitor the services we provide to you
  * For research, quality improvement activities (such as sending patient satisfaction surverys) and statistical analysis of data purposes
  * For any other purpose that may be identified to you before or at the time the information is collected
  * For purposes as mandated by law

## Disclosure of Your Personal Health Information

We disclose your personal health information to: 

  * Your ordering physician and members of your health care team who are copied on your requisition, often referred to as members within your “circle of care”
  * For the purpose of carrying out an investigation as a result of a court order, warrant, subpoena or summons or other purpose as permitted by law
  * To eliminate or reduce a significant risk of serious bodily harm to another person or group
  * For research purposes (only with your consent), subject to restrictions and conditions such as use of only certain set of data to meet a research objective
  * If permitted or prescribed by law

### Privacy Policy

Enhanced patient care delivery depends on a relationship of trust between our clients and staff. At LifeLabs, we respect your rights to access your personal health information and we work to ensure that personal health information is kept confidential while in our care.

  * **Accountability** : We are accountable to protect and safeguard your personal health information we collect, use and disclose. LifeLabs ensures that current privacy policies and procedures established are compliant with privacy legislation. Our Privacy Office conducts annual privacy training for staff, and conducts ongoing audits of our staff access to your personal health information. Our Privacy Office is available to respond to your privacy questions or concerns.
  * **Identifying Purposes** : We will identify the purpose for which personal information is collected at or before the time the information is collected.
  * **Consent** : LifeLabs operates on the order of your health care provider; therefore, consent may be implied for some defined circumstances. For example, when you visit one of our patient service centres with a test requisition from your physician, we rely on your implied consent not only to carry out those tests but to collect, use and disclose your personal health information in order to share the results with your health care providers. LifeLabs also posts notices in our patient service areas to advise you of the purposes for which we collect, use and disclose your personal health information. In some instances, LifeLabs will obtain your express consent when we collect, use and disclose your personal health information.   
**What is Implied consent:** implied consent is an assumption of permission to collect, use and disclose your personal information based on the fact that you presented yourself at our patient service centre for service. For example, your consent to collect, use and disclose your personal health information is implied in presenting your lab requisition when you come to one of our patient service centres for a blood test.   
**What is express consent:** this is consent provided either verbally or in writing, to LifeLabs to collect, use or disclose your personal health information except where otherwise required or permitted by applicable legislation. For example, we obtain your express consent when you request a hardcopy of your laboratory results.
  * **Limiting Collection** : LifeLabs will limit the collection of personal health information to that which is necessary for the authorized purposes identified. Information will be collected by fair and lawful means.
  * **Limiting Use, Disclosure and Retention** : Personal health information will not be used or disclosed for purposes other than those for which the information is collected or as required or permitted by law.

  * **Accuracy** : Personal health information will be as accurate, complete and up-to-date as is necessary for the purpose for which it is to be used.
  * **Safeguards** : LifeLabs takes security measures to ensure your personal health information is protected from loss, theft, unauthorized access, use, copying or disclosure. As a health information custodian, we review and update our security measures to meet industry standards. We have implemented safeguards to protect your personal information and these include but are not limited to:  
_Physical safeguards_ : locking filing cabinets and restricting access to our facilities to only authorized employees, vendors or visitors  
_Technical safeguards_ : passwords, encryptions and firewalls  
_Administrative safeguards_ : role based access, staff training, signing a confidentiality pledge.
  * **Openness** : At LifeLabs, we have communications posted in our patient waiting areas to notify you about our current practices in place to protect your personal health information. To ensure quality of service, we can communicate with you via telephone, in person and e-mail. We are committed to safeguarding your personal health information irrespective of the method through which we communicate with you.
  * **Individual Access** : We offer our patients online access to their test results. Patients with access to the internet can register free of charge to our _my results_ TM portal in Ontario and _my ehealth_ TM portal in BC to view their results.  
Not all test results are available on our portal; specifically, we don’t post, those results that are: sensitive in nature; controlled by regulatory requirements; sent to a government lab for analysis; or test results that are required to be reported directly to the ordering physician.   
If you do not have online access, you can request access to your results by completing one of the following forms:   
**Ontario:** [Access Request form](https://lifelabs.azureedge.net/lifelabs-wp-cdn/2018/09/Access-Request-Form-ONT.pdf)   
**British Columbia:** [Request for Patient’s Own Results ](https://lifelabs.azureedge.net/lifelabs-wp-cdn/2018/09/Access-Request-Form-BC.pdf)
  * **Challenging Compliance** : You may address your question(s) or complaint(s) concerning our compliance with privacy legislation to the Privacy Office via:  
Confidential e-mail: Privacy@LifeLabs.com  
Telephone: 1-844-783-6677

#### Access and Correction(s) 

**Access**

You can access your results from the following provinces where LifeLabs operates:

**Ontario and British Columbia                               **

  * LifeLabs online _my results_ TM – Ontario: <https://myresults.lifelabs.com/#/>
  * _my ehealth_ TM portal – British Columbia: <http://www.myehealth.ca/>
  * Written request submitted to our Privacy Office

**Ontario:** [Privacy Request form](https://lifelabs.azureedge.net/lifelabs-wp-cdn/2018/09/Privacy-request-form-ONT.pdf)  
**British Columbia:**[Privacy Request form](https://lifelabs.azureedge.net/lifelabs-wp-cdn/2018/09/Privacy-request-form-BC.pdf) 

  * Ordering physician: Contact your ordering physician to obtain your results

**Saskatchewan**

Please contact your physician to receive a copy of your test results. LifeLabs only provides collection services in Saskatchewan and does not process the samples.

**Correction(s)**

LifeLabs does not make corrections to test results, unless our Medical Science Department considers such a correction is compulsory and in compliance with applicable medical and legal requirements. If you disagree with a LifeLabs test result, it is best that you request your physician order a repeat of those tests that you disagree with. This will allow for a valid comparison of the results  
We will only make corrections to your demographic information (e.g. name, address, phone number) if the information we have about you is incorrect.

### Privacy Legislation and  Oversight Authorities

LifeLabs operates in two Canadian provinces: Ontario and B.C. Accordingly, we must comply with applicable provincial legislation as well as federal legislation. Our conduct in this regard is governed by the following laws and overseen by the following oversight authorities.

#### British Columbia

Relevant legislation: [Personal Information Protection Act (PIPA)](http://www.canlii.org/en/bc/laws/stat/sbc-2003-c-63/latest/sbc-2003-c-63.html)

Overseen by: Office of the Information & Privacy Commissioner for British Columbia

**Phone:**  
Toll-free: 1-800-663-7867   
Victoria: 250-387-5629   
Vancouver: 604-660-2421

Fax:  250-387-1696

**Email:**   [info@oipc.bc.ca](mailto:info@oipc.bc.ca)

**Mailing Address:**  
Office of the Information & Privacy Commissioner for British Columbia   
P.O. Box 9038, Stn. Prov. Govt.   
Victoria, BC  V8W 9A4

**Website:  **[www.oipc.bc.ca](http://www.oipc.bc.ca/)   

**What if I have a privacy concern or want to make a complaint?**

We take your privacy concerns and complaints seriously. If you have a privacy concern or complaint, you can contact us directly:

Contact our Privacy Office at 1-844-783-6677 or, our confidential e-mail: [privacy@lifelabs.com](mailto:privacy@lifelabs.com)

**If I sign up for the LifeLabs _my results_ TM / _my ehealth_** TM **portal, will others be able to access my information online?**

If you choose to sign up for **_my results_ TM /my ehealth**TM portal account, only you will have access to your personal health information on the website. **_my results_ TM /my ehealth**TM portal is a secure website that uses encryption technology and has strict password and security question rules. It is important that you do not share your password or security question answers with others. You should also make sure that you have logged-out of the system when you are finished viewing your results.

**Can my family see my personal health information?**

Although you have the right to access your information, this right does not automatically extend to family members and/or friends. Once LifeLabs receives your consent to share your personal health information with your family member and/or friend, that individual will receive access.

**Can all LifeLabs staff access my personal health information?**

Only LifeLabs staff involved in your care can access your record. All LifeLabs staff are bound by a strict confidentiality agreement, which is signed as a condition of employment and re-attested to annually. The purpose of this agreement is to ensure staff know that they are only allowed to access information that is required to perform their duties. Staff access to patient records is monitored to ensure that the privacy of your information is respected.
